Your Majesty,
陛下
this is the divorce agreement between Young Lady Xie and me.
这是臣与谢氏女的和离书
The bond between her and me ends here.
臣与她缘尽于此
This is for your review.
特呈御览
Your Majesty.
陛下
Regarding the Beifu Reform,
北府改制
what do you intend to do?
卿欲何为
Your Majesty,
回禀陛下
my reform will proceed in three steps.
臣之改制分三步而行
Firstly, eliminate long-standing flaws,
其一 革除积弊
restructure the military system,
整顿兵制
appoint talents of humble origins,
擢拔寒门才俊
and employ generals by ability alone.
不拘一格用将才
Secondly, forge stronger armor and weapons,
其二 精修甲胄兵械
and expand the transportation of provisions
广开粮秣漕运
to ensure steady military supplies.
使军需无虞
Thirdly...
其三
What is Prince Qi's take on this plan?
岐王对此策意下如何
Prince Qi and I share a bond like brothers
岐王与臣 情同手足
as well as deep trust.
肝胆相照
I believe that
臣相信
as long as His Highness and I join hands...
只要殿下与臣同心勠力
Even today,
时至今日
you still think
卿仍以为
that you and Prince Qi share a bond like brothers
岐王与你情同手足
as well as deep trust?
肝胆相照
Now,
现在
do you understand
卿可明白
why I insisted on keeping Xie Jiayu
朕为何执意要将谢嘉鱼
by your side?
留在你身边了吗
I understand now.
臣今日明白了
The way of checks and balances
制衡之道
is the emperor's art.
方是帝王心术
Therefore,
所以
Xie Jiayu
谢嘉鱼
is my way
便是朕
of keeping a balance between you and Prince Qi.
对你与岐王之间的制衡之道
Father, why are you so fond of pine trees?
父亲为何如此喜爱这松柏啊
They can endure cold and drought.
耐寒耐旱
Scatter a handful of seeds anywhere,
随便撒一把种子
and they will grow.
在哪儿都能活
But Mother told me that
可我听阿母说
you loved loquat flowers the most when you were young.
父亲少时最爱枇杷花了
Even Mother loved making loquat wine the most.
就连阿母也最爱酿这枇杷酒
People change.
人是会变的
I will set off for Jiankang in a few days.
令仪不日便要启程剑慷
I'm afraid that, by this time
来年此时
next year, I won't be able to accompany you
怕是不能陪同父亲
to pay respects to Mother together.
一同祭奠阿母了
Today,
今日
let me pour wine for you
就让令仪最后再为阿父
one last time, Father.
斟一次酒吧
You have arranged such a grand marriage
父亲为女儿寻了这样一门
for me, Father,
天大的婚事
but I only feel restless and uneasy.
女儿却只觉得惶恐
The Cui family is hailed as the top noble family.
崔氏号称天下第一世家
But what have you done, Father?
可父亲做过什么
Do you really think no one knows?
当真以为天下人不知吗
You've privately run illegal mines
私开矿藏
and tricked women
诱骗女子
into dying in the mines unjustly.
枉死于矿洞之中
Your actions are
父亲的所作所为
enough to ruin our Cui family completely.
足以令我崔氏万劫不复
Shao'an!
少安
You don't need to call him.
父亲不用叫了
I have already led Shao'an out of Lingfeng Fort.
我已将少安调离凌风堡
And I also told Xie Jiayu the hiding place
还将云昭郡主的藏身处
of her mother, Princess Yunzhao.
告知其女谢嘉鱼
By now, they must have left Lingfeng Fort.
此刻她们应该已经离开凌风堡
Everything about Lingfeng Fort is about to be exposed.
凌风堡的一切就要揭开了
Guards!
来人
If you plead guilty together with me today,
父亲今日与女儿一同伏法
our Cui family might still have a chance to survive.
我崔氏一门尚有一线生机
Lady Jiayu, my young lady ordered that
女郎 我家小姐吩咐
after we get Her Highness out,
一会儿接出郡主
you must leave Lingfeng Fort immediately.
女郎即刻离开凌风堡
Do you really think I'm stupid?
真当我傻呀
I knew Lingyi was a traitor
我早知阿姊吃里爬外
and wanted to help you save the Princess.
要帮你救出郡主
Where is Xiao Wuyi?
萧无衣呢
Behind you.
在你身后
Xiao Wuyi, how did you know there was a trap?
萧无衣 你怎知其中有诈
Were we also tricked by Young Lady Cui?
难道我们也被那个崔大女郎骗了
Cui Lingyi didn't trick us.
崔令仪没有骗我们
Instead, she was also deceived by them.
而是崔令仪也被他们骗了
Last night, Cui Lingyi spread the fake news
昨夜崔令仪放出我们
that we had fled from Lingfeng Fort.
逃离凌风堡的假消息
And you
而你
searched for us with great fanfare in the middle of the night.
三更半夜大张旗鼓追捕我们
Wasn't it to deliberately tell us that
不就是故意想要告诉我们
you had left the city?
你出城了吗
If my guess is right,
如果我没猜错的话
you lurked in the dark
你出城不久
soon after you left the city.
便偷偷潜伏下来
We encountered no obstacles at all
今日一路前往后山
on our way to the back mountain.
没有任何阻碍
Including that maid who suddenly appeared just now,
包括方才突然出现的侍女
everything is suspicious.
这一切都不合常理
Someone must have lured us here intentionally.
定是有人故意引我们到这里
You think you can bring me down this way?
你以为这样就可以扳倒为父
You think
你以为
you can save our Cui family just like this?
这样就可以拯救我崔氏门族
You think I would drink the poisoned wine?
你以为我会喝下毒酒
I am the Master of Lingfeng Fort.
为父才是这凌风堡的家主
And you will soon enter the Eastern Palace and marry
而你不日便要嫁入东宫
Prince Qi to become his consort.
成为岐王妃
In the future, you will be the first lady
日后会像文熹皇后那样
like Empress Wenxi.
母仪天下
Our Cui family has laid low for over 20 years
而我崔氏蛰伏二十余载
just for today
不就是为了今日
to revive our family.
可以重振我崔氏门族吗
But you insisted on ruining the glory of our Cui family
可是你 偏要在此时此刻
at this very moment
断送我崔氏门族的荣耀
and destroying my 20 years of great efforts.
毁了阿父二十年来的心血
I suppose your sister
想必你的阿姊
has already been captured by now.
此刻已经被俘了吧
Hand over the Princess,
把郡主交出来
or I'll kill you right now.
否则我现在就要了你的命
Ouch! It hurts...
疼 疼 疼
Mother!
阿母
What an impressive scheme.
好算计
Young Lord Xiao,
萧世子
I've heard a lot about you.
久仰大名
Put the sword down.
把剑放下
Father.
阿父
Lingyi is already engaged
阿姊已有婚约
and will get married soon.
不日便要完婚
Xiao Wuyi and the Princess
如今萧无衣和郡主
are both in our hands now.
都在我们手中
There won't be any problem.
并没有什么大碍
Please let Lingyi go, Father.
还请阿父放过阿姊
Father,
阿父
are you still going to use me
您还要继续利用我
to force Shao'an to do evil?
来威胁少安行恶吗
Lingyi...
阿姊
Are you still going to use Shao'an to force me
还要继续再用少安胁迫我
to cover up the truth for the family?
为家族掩盖真相吗
Since we were young,
从小到大
you've kept instigating conflicts between Shao'an and me.
您每每挑拨我与少安相争
Whenever you praised me,
您夸奖我时
you'd scold Shao'an
总会将少安
as if he was worthless.
训斥得一无是处
I didn't understand back then.
少时我不懂
I was only at odds with Shao'an
不过是为了讨好您
in order to please you.
才会与我的阿弟针锋相对
What you want is never children,
您要的根本就不是儿女
but merely
不过是两个
two pawns under your control!
任你摆布的棋子罢了
I'd rather die than be manipulated by you again!
我宁死也不会再受你摆布了
Do you think Princess Yunzhao
你以为云昭郡主
is some sort of good person?
是什么良善之人
Do you think she stayed
你以为她是为了
in order to expose the Cui family?
揭发崔氏而留下来
Do you think she lured Xiao Wuyi
你以为她引来萧无衣
over here to help you reveal
是为了帮助你揭开
the dark side of the Cui family?
崔家的丑恶
Everything she did was for the Phoenix Heart Token I hold!
她是为我手中雀骨令
Whatever her purpose,
我不管她是为了什么
all I want is for her to destroy
我只要她能毁掉
everything here!
这里的一切就够了
Lingyi,
阿姊
how could you talk to Father like that?
你怎么能这么跟父亲说话呢
Kneel and apologize to him!
跪下 给父亲道歉
Shao'an,
少安
the real lunatic in our family
咱们家真正疯了的人
is our father!
是我们的好父亲
Lingyi...
阿姊
Princess Yunzhao,
云昭郡主
your daughter and your reinforcement
你的女儿和救兵
are both in my hands.
都落在我的手中
Do you still refuse to hand over the Phoenix Heart Token?
还不交出雀骨令吗
Mother.
阿母
Are you alright?
你怎么样
Cui Jun, how dare you
崔浚 你好大的胆子
tamper with my letter?
竟敢篡改我的信
I did use the family letter to inform Xiao Wuyi,
我是借家书通知萧无衣
but I did something with the letter.
但我在信上做了手脚
It should never have reached Jiayu.
万万到不了嘉鱼那里
You deliberately set it up
是你故意设计
to lure Jiayu over here.
引嘉鱼来此
Yes, I did it.
是我
I also needed to know
我也要知道
who you plotted to get the Phoenix Heart Token
郡主图谋雀骨令和矿藏
and the mines for, right?
是为了谁吧
Mother,
阿母
what does he mean?
这是什么意思
Your Highness, you're indeed a good mother.
郡主果真是位好母亲
Everything you did was for your daughter.
这一切都是为了你的女儿
System reform, northern expedition—
改制 北伐
actually, the one who really needs the minerals
其实真正需要矿藏的
is Young Lord Xiao.
是萧世子
But your daughter is in his hands.
可是女儿又在人家手中
As her mother, of course you have to yield.
做母亲的怎能不低头啊
Therefore, you came to Guazhou for Young Lord Xiao
于是你是为了萧世子来到鸹州
to find the Phoenix Heart Token.
寻找雀骨令
So you really have
雀骨令
the Phoenix Heart Token.
果真在你手上
You found this mine
这个矿山
under the guidance of the Phoenix Heart Token.
就是你根据雀骨令的指引找到的
I have indeed decoded it.
我的确是破解了
So there's no way I can let you go.
所以就更不可能放你们走
Cui Jun,
崔浚
even if you kill and silence us all, the secret
就算你们把我们都杀了灭口
of the Cuis and the Phoenix Heart Token still can't remain hidden.
崔家和雀骨令的事情也瞒不住
Young Lord Xiao,
萧世子
instead of worrying about me,
你为老夫操心
right now,
眼下
you'd better worry about yourself.
不如操心操心自己吧
The secret guards you planted have been exposed.
你安插的暗卫已经暴露
No one will come to save you anymore.
没有人会来救你了
Princess, I'll only give you 2 days.
郡主 我只给你两日时间
If you still refuse to hand over the Phoenix Heart Token,
若还不肯交出雀骨令
your daughter will die for sure.
你的女儿就死定了
Look what I got for you.
你看我给你带了什么
I didn't expect that, after so many years,
没想到这么多年
you still remember that I
老师还记得学生
love the longans from Nanzhou the most, Master.
最钟爱这南洲的龙眼
This time,
你这一次
you did a great job.
做得很好
You sent Cui Jun's contaminated military provisions
将崔浚那些被污染的军粮
to the Northern Border,
送到了北境
leading to an outbreak of plague in the Beifu Army.
令北府军中突发疫病
It also caused the noble families
如此也令世家们
to impeach the Beifu Reform one after another
纷纷弹劾北府改制
and quietly
又神不知鬼不觉地
lured Xiao Wuyi to Cui Jun's place.
将萧无衣引到崔浚处
It's been over 2 decades.
二十多年了
This grudge should finally come to an end.
这场恩怨总该有个了结
Master,
老师
I heard that the unjust case of the An and Lu families back then
学生听闻当年安陆二氏的冤案
was all traced back to Empress Wenxi of the Cui family.
正是从崔氏文熹皇后而起
Is it true?
莫非是真的
If Xiao Wuyi can bring down
若萧无衣这一次
the Cuis, Empress Wenxi's maternal family,
能把文熹皇后的母家
this time,
崔氏给办了
the secret of the An and Lu families from back then
那当年安陆的秘密
might finally come to light.
或许就能大白于世
If so,
若真如此
you will be
你便是我
my greatest benefactor
谢怀归此生
for the rest of my life.
最大的恩人
Your grace of teaching gave me a second life,
师恩再造
equal to my parents' care and love.
同于鞠育
Now that I got a chance to do you a favor,
得效犬马
even if I die for it,
虽陨首结草
I still can't repay you enough.
未足云报
It is already the greatest fortune of my life!
此生之至幸也
Master, we just got the news from the Court of Judicial Review.
家主 大理寺方才传来消息
Yang Zhang, Guazhou County Sheriff,
鸹州县尉杨章
committed suicide in prison out of fear.
已在狱中畏罪自杀
The body can't be kept.
尸体不能留
Send his body to Puzhao Temple tonight and burn it.
连夜送到普照寺烧了
Understood.
诺
Anything else?
还有事吗
The subordinates Young Lord Xiao planted outside Lingfeng Fort
萧世子安排在凌风堡外围的部下
have all been wiped out.
已被悉数剿灭
Cui Jun has captured Young Lord Xiao.
崔浚控制了萧世子
How could Xiao Wuyi have made
萧无衣的准备
such hasty preparations?
怎么会如此草率
Our informant reported
眼线回报
that Young Lord Xiao entered
萧世子是为了女郎
Lingfeng Fort early for our young lady.
提前进入了凌风堡
Xie Jiayu?
谢嘉鱼
How come she's in Guazhou?
她怎么会在鸹州呢
Not only the Young Lady,
不只女郎
but the Princess is also there.
还有郡主
Her Highness wrote to the Young Lady and made her go to Guazhou.
正是郡主传信女郎至鸹州
Cui Jun has seized them all now,
如今都被崔浚控制在手中
using the Young Lady to force Her Highness to hand over the Phoenix Heart Token.
用女郎威胁郡主交出雀骨令
The Phoenix Heart Token?
雀骨令
I see. Cui Jun is Empress Wenxi's older brother.
是了 崔浚乃文熹皇后兄长
If Yunzhao has the Phoenix Heart Token
若云昭手持雀骨令
and wants to unite her old subordinates against Prince Qi,
想要联合旧部对付岐王
Cui Jun is the best ally.
崔浚是最好的帮手
Xiao Wuyi,
萧无衣
was Cui Jun telling the truth
方才崔浚所言
just now?
是真的吗
Did my mother look for
我阿母是为了你
the Phoenix Heart Tokens for you?
才找的雀骨令
Yes.
是
You could say that.
可以这么说
My mother never meddles in court politics.
我阿母向来不参与朝局
If someone hadn't forced her,
若非有人逼迫
she wouldn't have taken the initiative to get involved.
她不会主动涉入其中
Did you use me to threaten her?
你拿我威胁她了
No,
没有
I've never used you to threaten her.
我从未拿你威胁过她
But this matter is complicated.
但这其中曲折复杂
I'll explain it to you later.
我日后再与你解释
But my mother agreed to help you
但我阿母就是为了我
because of me.
才答应你的
I once thought that after my mother and father divorced,
我以为阿母和阿父和离之后
she would finally be able to live for herself,
她终于能过上自己的人生
travel to places she had never seen,
去看她从未看过的山川湖海
and lead a carefree life she had never had.
去过她从没有过过的恣意人生
I didn't expect that
没想到
she'd still be dragged into this because of me,
却还是被我连累
utilized by others,
被人利用
and end up in such a desperate state.
走到这绝处来
I once thought that
我还以为
you cared about me in Prince Jing'an's Mansion
你在靖安王府对我的那些照顾
and allowed me to come and go freely,
你任我来去自由
all because you were just a good person.
是因为你就是一个好人
I was too stupid.
是我太蠢了
Everything I did
我所做的一切
was never about
从来都不是为了
making a deal with the Princess.
与郡主做交易
Xie Jiayu,
谢嘉鱼
did you really not
难道你一丝一毫
feel anything at all?
都没有感受到吗
Am I wrong, Xiao Wuyi?
难道不是吗 萧无衣
You've been using me from the very beginning.
你从头到尾都在利用我
At first, when you didn't even know who I was,
你一开始不知道我是谁时
you used me to quell Prince Changsha's rebellion.
就利用我平息长沙王之乱
When you knew who I was,
等你知道我是谁了
you used my freedom
就利用我的自由
and my life
用我的性命
to force my mother to hand over the Phoenix Heart Token,
来逼迫我阿母交出雀骨令
putting her in danger!
让我阿母身陷险境
Yes.
是
It's all my fault.
都怪我
What is this sound?
这是什么声音
Not the sound of a human.
不是人的声音
There is an underground river beneath this mine,
这座矿山下有条地下河
where the water is not clean.
水不干净
Taken or applied,
或饮或用
it drives people mad
就会让人精神狂躁
and turns them into beasts,
宛如野兽
just like him.
就像他一样
Do you know how many people my father had killed
你可知我阿父用多少条人命
until he got such a monster?
才喂出这么一只怪物吗
No more struggling.
别挣扎了
This candle is specially made.
这烛火是特制的
You can't use your martial arts anymore.
你的武功使不出来
Hand over the Phoenix Heart Token.
交出雀骨令
Otherwise,
否则
I don't mind letting this monster
我不介意让这个怪物
deal with Xie Jiayu.
会会谢嘉鱼
Very well.
好
Release him.
把他给我放开
Jiayu!
嘉鱼
Xiao Wuyi!
萧无衣
-Stay here and watch. -Xiao Wuyi!
在这儿看着 萧无衣
He has little inner energy now.
他如今没什么内力
How about we give him 15 minutes?
给他半炷香如何
It won't take him 15 minutes.
他不需要半炷香
You trust him that much?
这么信任他
He will win for sure.
他一定会赢
Xiao Wuyi...
萧无衣
Grand Tutor, you must've come
太傅漏夜前来
late at night for something important.
想必是有很重要的事吧
What on earth happened?
究竟发生了何事
Have you heard of the Phoenix Heart Tokens?
听过雀骨令吗
When the Phoenix Heart Tokens appear, peace shall be restored in the world.
雀骨出 天下定
Who in Ye hasn't heard about it?
大邺人谁没有听过这样的传言
It is the hope of the people.
这是百姓心中的寄托
What if Empress Wenxi really had the Phoenix Heart Tokens
如果文熹皇后真有雀骨令
and passed them down?
流传于世呢
Since Yunzhao was her closest friend,
而云昭身为其闺中密友
and Cui Jun was her older brother,
崔浚身为其兄
the two of them are the most likely
他们二人最有可能
to be entrusted by Empress Wenxi.
成为文熹皇后托付信任之人
Even if the Phoenix Heart Tokens truly exist,
即便这雀骨令确有其事
the Northern Qin people back then
可北秦人当年
already wiped out Crown Prince Wenxi.
早就将文熹太子斩草除根
Those people only have the Phoenix Heart Tokens
他们那群人空有雀骨令
but not Crown Prince Wenxi.
却没有文熹太子
They pose no threat to my brother at all.
对我哥哥根本就造不成威胁
Your Highness,
县主
what if I told you
若我告诉你
your brother
你哥哥
is not of the Ye bloodline at all?
根本不是大邺血脉呢
Watch your words, Grand Tutor.
太傅慎言
Yunzhao has long suspected Prince Qi's origins.
云昭早就怀疑岐王的身世
She went to Guazhou this time
她此番去鸹州
probably just to use
恐怕就是要用
the Phoenix Heart Token in her hands
自己手上的雀骨令
to command the other Token holders
去号令其他持令之人
and support the Imperial Li family of Ye again.
重新扶持李邺宗室
How is that possible?
怎么可能
How could my brother not be...
我哥哥他怎么可能不
Your trip to Guazhou this time
你此番去鸹州
is nominally to escort the bride,
名义上是去迎亲
but the real purpose is to cooperate
实际上是要配合
with Young Lord Xiao to capture the Cuis.
萧世子捉拿崔氏
Remember, besides purging the Cuis,
记住 除了剿灭崔氏之外
you absolutely cannot let the Phoenix Heart Token
绝对不能让雀骨令
fall into Xiao Wuyi's hands.
落入萧无衣的手上
You must not
绝对
let Yunzhao ruin Prince Qi's future.
不能让云昭毁了岐王的未来
Brother, the clothes are fixed.
阿兄 衣服缝好了
Try them on when you're free.
你有时间了就试一下
Lejun.
乐君
Put this on.
把这个戴上
This sachet
这香囊
was sewn for you
还是当年
by Mother back then.
阿娘亲手为你缝的
I heard that a strange disease is raging in Guazhou.
听说鸹州怪病肆虐
It has Bishou lotuses inside,
里边有碧首莲
with detoxifying effects.
有祛毒之效
Since this was made by Mother,
此物既是阿娘所做
it can definitely keep you safe on your journey.
想必能护你一路平安
Brother, you are so silly.
哥哥真是傻子
It's been so many years.
都过了这么多年了
The effects must've long worn off.
药效早就没了
You will always be my brother.
哥哥就是哥哥
The brother I know
我所认识的哥哥
is Li Mao, who has always
就是和我一起
stuck with me through everything.
相依为命的李茂
What?
什么
Don't worry, Brother.
兄长放心
I will not fail your trust on this journey.
臣妹此行定不负兄长所托
I will bring the Cui family to justice
捉拿崔氏归案
and return safe and sound.
平安归来
You irritated me
你方才
on purpose just now
故意激将我
because you wanted me to help you kill him, right?
就是想让我替你杀了他吧
I've been sick of that bastard for a long time.
我早看那个畜生不爽了
You hated what your father has done,
你对你爹的所作所为不满
but you didn't dare to resist.
但你又不敢反抗
So you could only use Xiao Wuyi and me as pawns.
所以只能拿我和萧无衣作筏子
My father would do anything
我爹为了雀骨令
for the Phoenix Heart Tokens.
什么都能干得出来
I needed to see
我总要看看你们
your determination and capabilities
到底有什么决心和能力
to go against my father.
敢跟我爹对着干吧
Xiao Wuyi,
萧无衣
when will your men arrive?
你的人什么时候到
It's fine if you don't want to tell me,
不想说没关系
as long as there are reinforcements.
只要有援兵就行
The area outside the cave is heavily guarded by my father's men.
这洞外都是我阿父的人
You'd better not act rashly
援军未至
before the reinforcements arrive.
最好不要轻易行动
I'll remove all the candles outside.
我会把外面的蜡烛都撤掉
This is the only thing I can do for you.
这是我唯一能帮你们的了
Hold on.
等等
This is what your sister asked me to give
这是你阿姊生前
to you when she was alive.
托我转交给你的
If this plan fails tomorrow,
若明日此举不成
I will definitely end up dead.
我必遭杀身之祸
Please pass this letter on to my brother.
请将此信交与我阿弟
If you are going to make a move,
你们若要行动
you'd better rescue all the people below.
最好把底下的人都救出来
When will your reinforcements arrive?
你的援兵什么时候到
Qing Long and Yan Yue will send word.
青龙 偃月会给信的
Don't worry,
放心吧
they will definitely ensure the safety
一定会先保证郡主
of the Princess and Yuan Xiaoliu first.
和元小六的安全
Then let's rest
那先休息吧
to conserve our strength.
养精蓄锐
♪ Fear no partings or wax and wane ♪
你别多想
I'm just afraid your injuries are too severe
我是怕你伤势太重
for you to make it out of here alive.
别到时候死在这儿
I...
我
I'm not treating you well because of the Phoenix Heart Token
我不是为了郡主给我的雀骨令
that the Princess gave me.
才对你好的
Both Her Highness and I
我和郡主一样
wish for you to live freely and happily.
都希望你自由快乐地活着
Jiayu.
嘉鱼
I...
我
♪ Bear witness with our souls ♪
萧无衣
Are you sure
你确定
♪ Fear no partings or wax and wane ♪
你能把那些人都救出来吗
I can.
我能
♪ You know me, seeing things through from start to finish ♪
说大话
I can pull it off if you trust me.
你信我 我就能
Okay.
好
♪ Burn the fire in my heart ♪
我相信你
I know this risky path I walk may lead only to death.
我此番冒险自知凶多吉少
However, the Cui family's evil deeds actually started because of me.
然崔家之恶 实由我起
If I hadn't tried to outdo you
若非当年我与你争一时意气
and reminded Father that, compared to adult men,
提醒父亲矿道狭窄
perhaps women might be better suited
比起成年男子
to the narrow mine tunnels
或许女子更为灵活
and wouldn't be discovered by the authorities,
且不会被官府发现
we wouldn't have committed so many murders now.
如今也不会造下这么多杀孽
Plenty of women were tricked into coming to Lingfeng Fort
那么多女子被诓骗至凌风堡
and lost their lives for a bit of grain and money.
为一粟米 一吊钱没了命
Thankfully, Princess Yunzhao discovered the secret of the mines.
幸而云昭郡主发现矿洞隐秘
I saved her
我救她
and helped her lure Young Lord Xiao here
替她引来萧世子
in order to atone for my sins.
是为赎罪
Shao'an, I know you want me to leave Lingfeng Fort
阿弟 我知你想让我离开凌风堡
and live a peaceful life.
安稳余生
But since the mistake has been made, I must pay with my life.
可错已铸成 便当赔命
If you continue to help the evildoer,
你若继续助纣为虐
I will not be able to rest in peace.
我亦泉下难眠
I hope my death can ignite your will to live.
望我一死 燃你生志
Only you know the way to save those women.
只有你知道该如何解救那些女子
Hey!
来人哪
Who the heck locked me up?
到底是谁绑的老子
Say something!
说话
It's been so many days,
这么多天了
and no one's ever come!
一个人都没有
Why not kill him, Master?
主君为何不杀了他
What if...
万一
Prince Qi's escort team
岐王的迎亲队伍
is already near Guazhou.
已经在鸹州外了
Princess Pingning
这一回
came in person this time.
是平宁县主亲自来了
They came right on time.
来得正是时候
How many days has it been since we last heard from Cui Xi?
崔喜几日没有消息了
There are new updates every day.
日日都有新消息传来
Everything is as usual at the Cui Mansion in Jiankang.
剑慷崔府一切如常
I see.
知道了
By the way,
对了
you must not mistreat him.
千万不要亏待他
Understood.
诺
Are you kidnapping me for my money or my looks?
劫财还是劫色
Just tell me directly!
给句痛快话
I'm fine with either!
我都行
Greetings, Father.
参见父亲
Prince Qi has sent his younger sister,
岐王已经派他的妹妹
Princess Pingning,
平宁县主
to Lingfeng Fortress to escort the bride.
来我凌风堡迎亲
From now on,
从今往后
she will be your older sister,
她就是你的阿姊
Cui Lingyi.
崔令仪
Father.
父亲
She is not my...
她不是我
Turn your head around.
把头转过来
Bow.
行礼
S-Sister.
阿 阿姊
Xie Jiayu
谢嘉鱼
made the white silk flower for your sister, right?
给你阿姊扎的白绢花对不对
Didn't you miss your sister so much?
你不是很想念你的阿姊吗
Then stay here and behave yourself.
那就给我好好地待在这儿
Without my order,
没有我的命令
you shall not leave this place even by a single step.
不准离开这里半步
I spent over 20 years
老夫用了二十余载
cracking the secret in the Phoenix Heart Token
才破解了这雀骨令中的奥秘
and discovering the iron mine under this mountain.
发现了这座山下的铁矿
But it's a pity that
只可惜啊
an accident happened halfway through the excavation.
刚挖到一半就出事了
The groundwater has been contaminated,
地下水被污染
and anyone who touches it will get hit by a strange disease.
凡沾染者皆得怪病
Last night, Xiao Wuyi
昨夜萧无衣
killed a maniac with the strange disease.
斩杀了一个染怪病的疯子
Your Highness, if you still refuse to hand over the Phoenix Heart Token,
如若郡主再不肯交出雀骨令
then the next one to get infected
那么下一个染病的
will be Xie Jiayu.
就是谢嘉鱼
If she gets infected,
若她染病
I wonder if Young Lord Xiao
不知萧世子
would give her a quick death.
可愿给她一个痛快
Take this hairpin
拿着这个发簪
and go to the Nandu Wharf we agreed on back then.
去当年约定的南渡码头
Seeing this hairpin,
此簪在手
someone will contact you.
自然会有人联络你
I can't believe you hid the Phoenix Heart Token
你竟然将雀骨令
at the old Nandu Wharf.
藏在当年的南渡码头
Guards,
来人
seal off all the mines at the foot of the mountain
将山下的矿洞通通填埋
and let no one get out of there.
任何人不准离开矿洞一步
-Understood.
诺
Take Her Highness away
将郡主带下去
and lock her up.
看押起来
Cui Jun!
崔浚
You broke your word!
你言而无信
It's not the first time.
又不是头一回了
Aren't you afraid that everything I told you is fake?
你就不怕我告诉你的全是假的
The worst case is that I'll kill both you
大不了送你和你女儿
and your daughter.
一起上路
Take her away.
带下去
Stop wandering. You're making me dizzy.
别走了 走得我头都晕了
Do you think Qing Long and Yan Yue have been caught?
你说青龙 偃月会不会被抓住了
Where are your reinforcements?
你的那些援兵呢
Why hasn't there been any response?
怎么一点反应都没有
Rest assured.
放心吧
Before I entered Lingfeng Fort,
在我入凌风堡前
the reinforcements were already on their way.
那些援兵就已经在路上了
I didn't come here because of
我并不是被郡主的家书
the Princess's family letter.
引来此处的
Before I came here,
来此之前
some people in the Beifu Army
北府军中就有人
contracted the same strange disease as those in the mines.
得了和矿洞那些人一样的怪病
They ate the rations issued by the imperial court
他们吃了朝廷下发的
that had been soaked in contaminated water.
被污水浸泡过的军粮
And those rations came from Guazhou.
而那些军粮就出自于鸹州
Someone must have learned the secret about Guazhou
定是有人得知了鸹州的消息
and dragged the Beifu soldiers into this
拖北府兵下水
just in order to lure me here.
就是想引我来此处
It can not only deal a blow to the Beifu Reform
既能打击北府改制
but also destroy the Cui family.
又能置崔家于死地
I guess the person behind this
我想这背后之人
is the Grand Tutor.
是太傅
My father?
我阿父
The Grand Tutor and the Cui family
太傅与崔氏
probably have a blood feud.
恐有灭门之仇
Judging from the time,
按时间来算
Li Mao must have
李茂此刻
raided the Cui Mansion in Jiankang by now.
应该已对剑慷的崔府下手了
The people he dispatched from Jiankang
他从剑慷安排过来的人
should arrive in a few days.
应该不日就到
You... Why didn't you tell me earlier?
你 你怎么不早说
You guys, go there.
你们 去那儿
-Understood!
诺
And you.
你
They are locked up in the cell ahead.
他们就关在前面的牢房
Understood.
诺
What is he doing here?
他来干什么
Sealing off the mines.
封矿
Don't be afraid.
别怕
According to my master's order,
主君吩咐了
you two are distinguished guests,
二位是贵客
and the path to the afterlife is a painful one.
黄泉路上不好走
If you want to die a quick death,
若想干脆些
you can take this poison.
可用此药
It seems that Cui Jun
看来这崔浚
really wants me dead.
还真想置我于死地啊
Master!
师父
Where have you been the past few days?
你这两日都到哪儿去了
I don't even want to bring it up. You wouldn't believe me.
别提了 我说了你都不信
The past few days,
这几天
I've been eating well for all 3 meals every day.
我一日三餐 吃香的喝辣的
Except for that mute who delivered the food,
除了那个送饭的哑巴
I didn't see anyone else.
我一个人都见不到
Wait,
不是
w-why? There's no way!
我 我们凭什么
Look...
你看 你 你
Hurry.
快快快
Sorry.
不好意思啊
Where are Qing Long and Yan Yue?
青龙 偃月呢
You were not led here by them?
不是他们引你过来的
No.
不是啊
It was Cui Shao'an.
是崔少安
The mines in the back mountain.
后山矿洞
The Cui family is grateful for His Majesty's grace.
崔氏感念皇恩浩荡
I am willing to be diligent and self-disciplined,
崔某愿当勤谨克己
strictly follow the imperial edict,
谨遵圣意
form a marriage alliance with Prince Qi,
与岐王殿下缔结良缘
and devote my absolute loyalty and effort to the state.
为社稷尽忠 效命万分
I will not fail His Majesty's grace.
不负天恩
I, Cui Lingyi, am willing to serve Prince Qi
臣妾崔氏令仪愿侍奉殿下
and be of one mind and principle with His Highness
与殿下同心同德
to protect our family and state,
护持家国
with fidelity for the rest of my life.
不负此生
You may rise.
起来吧
Wait!
慢着
You rebellious child!
逆子
Today is your sister's big day of being escorted as the bride.
今日是你阿姊迎亲之日
What are you going to do?
你想干什么
Guards! Take my unfilial son out!
来人 将这个不孝子给我拖出去
I, Cui Shao'an, pay my respects
罪臣崔少安
to you, Princess Pingning.
拜见平宁县主
You killed...
你居然杀了
The one I killed is not my real sister.
罪臣杀的并非我亲生阿姊
You brat!
逆子
Cui Shao'an,
崔少安
what did you just say?
你方才说什么
My sister, Cui Lingyi,
罪臣的阿姊崔令仪
was killed by my father long ago,
早已被我阿父亲手杀害
with her body destroyed overnight.
连夜毁尸灭迹
If you don't believe me,
若县主不信
Your Highness, here is my sister's handwritten letter
这里有我阿姊亲笔手书
as well as the evidence of the crimes that my Cui family
还有我阿姊冒死留下的
has committed over the past 20 years,
关于我崔氏一门
which my sister left behind at the price of her life!
二十年来的种种罪证
Please take a look, Your Highness!
请县主过目
What are these bloody contracts?
这一张张血契书算什么
Cui Jun, you've not only run illegal private mines
崔浚 你不仅开私矿
but also harmed young girls and children
还残害少女孩童
and made them mine for you,
为你挖矿
causing countless unjust deaths.
令多少人枉死
Do you even care about the imperial court and the people?
你将朝廷和百姓置于何地
How can you claim to stand with Prince Qi
又何谈与岐王殿下
in protecting the state
护持家国
and carrying out a great cause?
共担大义
Guards!
来人哪
Your Highness, you came to Lingfeng Fort with the armed Imperial Guards
县主假借迎亲之名
under the guise of escorting the bride.
却内藏禁军之刃
What are you up to?
来我凌风堡所为何意
Cui Jun, are you trying to rebel?
崔浚 你是想造反吗
Listen up, guys.
你们听着
Whoever kills Li Lejun will be
杀李乐君者
rewarded with 1,000 households' tax revenues and 10,000 taels of gold!
赏千户 金万两
Brother!
哥哥
Sister!
妹妹
Kill them, and you'll be
杀了他们
rewarded based on merits!
论功行赏
Who dares to make a move?
我看你们谁敢
We're standing here today.
今日我们就站在这里
You can make your move
你们可以动手
and kill all of us!
可以杀死我们所有人
But look at these faces.
但请看看这些面孔
Are they any different
她们和你们的骨肉至亲
from your own families?
有何分别
If you raise your blades to kill us today,
今日你们举起屠刀
someone will use the same blades
明日就会有人把同样的刀刃
to murder your families tomorrow!
架在你们亲人的脖颈之上
Bring her here!
把人给我带上来
Mother!
阿母
Xie Jiayu, Xiao Wuyi,
谢嘉鱼 萧无衣
if you take one more step forward,
再向前一步
I'll have Yunzhao
我就让云昭
die in front of you right away.
立刻死在你们面前
Cui Jun,
崔浚
don't you dare.
你敢
Xiao Wuyi, you...
萧无衣 你
This is the Beifu Army's war drum.
这是北府军的战鼓声
Xiao Wuyi,
萧无衣
when did you set this up?
你是何时布的局
Since the moment Princess Yunzhao told you
从郡主将雀骨令下落
the Phoenix Heart Token's whereabouts.
告诉你的那一刻
Qing Long, Yan Yue!
青龙 偃月
This is the totem of Northern Qin's Eagle King.
这是北秦鹰王的图腾
Yes, they are all the Eagle King's henchmen
没错 都是北秦人
from Northern Qin.
鹰王的爪牙
Cui Jun,
崔浚
the Eagle King of Northern Qin is the client of your private mines.
北秦鹰王就是你的私矿买家
You have been colluding with Northern Qin all along.
你一直与北秦勾结
How audacious you are.
你好大的胆子
Cui Jun,
崔浚
over 20 years ago,
二十多年前
when Northern Qin attacked the Capital,
北秦攻打上京
you were accusing
正是你首告
the An and Lu families for the first time.
安陆两大世家之时
Could it be that you had already colluded with Northern Qin back then,
莫非从那时你就勾结了北秦
causing the horrible bloodshed in the Capital?
这才造成了上京城内血流漂杵
What horrible bloodshed?
什么血流漂杵
I only know that the Ans and Lus conspired with the enemy and committed treason.
我只知道安陆两家里通卖国
I only know that Emperor Wenxi was licentious and brutal,
只知道文熹帝荒淫无道
bringing destruction to the state and families.
弄得国破家亡
How dare you!
放肆
How dare you slander the late Emperor?
你竟敢诬蔑先帝
Don't forget that
莫忘了
you are Empress Wenxi's brother
你是文熹皇后的哥哥
and the Phoenix Heart Token holder,
也是雀骨令的持令人
bearing the responsibility of moving Ye south
都肩负着大邺南渡
and assisting Crown Prince Wenxi...
辅佐文熹太子
Crown Prince Wenxi died long ago!
文熹太子早死了
He is not dead!
他没有死
Crown Prince Wenxi is not dead?
文熹太子没有死
Tell me.
告诉我
Who is Crown Prince Wenxi?
文熹太子他是谁
Where is he hiding?
藏在哪里
Mother!
阿母
Are you okay?
没事吧
I'm fine.
没事